Guide to the Bruce Lawrence Papers, 1980-2009 UA.29.02.0256
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bruce Lawrence Papers
1980-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lawrence, Bruce B.
UA.29.02.0256
3.0 Linear Feet
Bruce Lawrence is a professor in the Department of Religion and the founding director of the Duke Islamic Studies Center (DISC). The Bruce Lawrence papers include materials related to the founding of DISC as well as other programs and projects related to Islam and Middle East Studies both at Duke and elsewhere.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Duke Administrative Materials and Professional Activities.
Biographical / Historical
Bruce Lawrence was born in Netwon, New Jersey in 1941. He graduated Princeton University in 1962 with a BA in Near Eastern Studies, served in the U.S. Navy from 1962-1964, graduated from the Episcopal Divinity School in Cambridge, Massachusetts, with an M. Div in Biblical Studies, and graduate from Yale University in 1972 with a Ph.D, studying Hiduism and Islam.
Lawrence joined the faculty of Duke University in 1971, in the Department of Religion. He taught and continued his research in comparative study of religious movements and institutional Islam. He was instrumental in the creation of the Carolina-Duke-Emory Institute for the Study of Islam (CDEISI) in 1997, which later evolved into the Center for the Study of Muslim Networks in 2002. In 2006, the Duke Islamic Studies Center (DISC) was formally established, with Bruce Lawrence as the founding director. DISC is an interdisciplinary center that, as of 2016, offers a Focus Program cluster and a DukeEngage Program, hosts a number of programs and events including speakers, panels, and film screenings, and sponsors initiatives such as the Transcultural Islam Project and ISLAMiCommentary.
Bruce Lawrence has written a number of books including Defenders of God: The Fundamentalist Revolt Against the Modern Age(1989), Shattering the Myth: Islam Beyond Violence (1998), The Qur'an: Books that Changed the World (2008), and Who is Allah? (2015). He was awarded two Fulbright Scholarships (1995 and 2006) and selected as a Carnegie Corporation Scholar of Islam in 2008.
He married fellow Duke professor miriam cooke in 1983.
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use these records.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Bruce Lawrence Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 2016.
Related Materials
Dept. of Religion records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Islamic and Arabian Development Studies Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Morocco at Duke scrapbook, 1985 Sept., Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The collection includes materials related to the work of Bruce Lawrence at Duke University, particularly related to the development and work of the Duke Islamic Studies Center (DISC). Topics covered include Duke centers and programs related to Islamic and Middle Eastern Studies; work in and relationships with the country of Morocco, including cultural and arts festivals, a partnership between Duke University and Mohammed V University, and a Duke-in-Morocco program, some of which includes correspondence with Angier Biddle Duke; international seminars and programs (including some in partnership with the Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, especially in Morocco); grant and funding applications (including several from the Pew Charitable Trusts); Islamic art and architecture; history of religions; South East Asia; and other topics. Materials include notes, correspondence, conference programs and flyers, news clippings, and research materials, among others.
Middle East -- Study and teaching -- United States; Civilization, Islamic -- Study and teaching; Islamic countries -- Study and teaching; Morocco -- Study and teaching; Lawrence, Bruce B.; Lawrence, Bruce B.; Duke University. Duke Islamic Studies Center.; Pew Charitable Trusts; Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies; Duke University. Department of Religion; Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995
- Duke Administrative Materials, 1996-2009; 1
  - Pew Trust: Muslim Networks, 2000-2003 (Box 1)
  - Muslim Networks, 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - Middle East/Islamic Studies, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Establishing a Center, 2005-2009; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Duke Islamic Studies Center (DISC), 2008; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Duke Islamic Studies Center (DISC), 2008-20009 (Box 1)
  - DISC Advisory Board Meeting, November 2009 (Box 1)
  - Duke Islamic Studies Center (DISC), 2009 (Box 1)
  - Department of Religion, 1996-2001; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Center for Genome Ethics, Law, and Policy (GELP), 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - International Studies, 2002-2004 (Box 1)
- Professional Activities, 1980-2009; 2
  - History of Religions colloquium, proposal, 1980-1984; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Aspen Institute: Marrekech seminar, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Material on colonialism and architecture in Morocco (REL 163 readings), 1980, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Morocco '86, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Aspen Institute: Morocco: Past, Present, and Future, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Morocco materials, 1982, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Morocco materials, 1986; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Pew Charitable Trust grant, 1985, 1991, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Forum on Global Islam, 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Forum on Global Islam, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Pew: Forum on Global Islam, May 1992 (Box 2)
  - JISC (Joint Information Systems Committee) proposal, 1998-2002 (Box 2)
  - Wiegand Foundation, 1998-2003; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Wiegand Foundation, 1999-2002 (Box 2)
  - Luce application: Arts and Religions, 2001 (Box 2)
  - South Asia, 2001-2002 (Box 2)
  - Ford grant: Difficult Dialogues, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Muslim cyberfile, 2006-2009 (Box 2)
  - Social Science Research Council: Muslim Modernities, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Qatar: Museum of Islamic Art, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Jeddah Economic Forum, 2008-2009; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Jeddah Economic Forum: Student papers, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Indonesia: Legacy International Religion and Society, other materials, 2008-2009 (Box 3)
  - Media Training Workshop, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Muslim Voices: Arts and Ideas at NYU Center for Dialogues, June 2009 (Box 3)
  - Muslim Voices: Arts and Ideas, NYU Center for Dialogues Conference on Bridging the Divide Conference Report, 2009 (Box 3)